<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A book of perspective &amp; geometry, being the ABC, and first degree of all good art The learning of which comprehendeth in it many notable arts, needfull and necessary for every artificer and workman. For as no perspective workman can make any work without architecture, so neither can the architecture without perspective. Which perspective is inspection or looking into by shortning of the sight, making it to shew further then in effect it is. ... And seing [sic] perspective art is nothing without geometry, they are both bound together, that the workman may be able to aide and help himselfe therewith. And forasmuch as the hand cannot effect the understanding of the mind, I shall not please thereby such as are curious, yet at least I shall help yong beginners that know little or nothing thereof. This second book of architecture made by Sebastian Serly, entreating of perspective, touching the superficies, translated out of Itallian into Dutch, and out of Dutch into English, ...</title>
            <title>Tutte l'opere d'architettura. Book 2. English</title>
            <author>Serlio, Sebastiano, 1475-1554.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 101 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59260</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2623</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223996</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99834706</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99834706</idno>
            <idno type="VID">39210</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59260)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 39210)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1819:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A book of perspective &amp; geometry, being the ABC, and first degree of all good art The learning of which comprehendeth in it many notable arts, needfull and necessary for every artificer and workman. For as no perspective workman can make any work without architecture, so neither can the architecture without perspective. Which perspective is inspection or looking into by shortning of the sight, making it to shew further then in effect it is. ... And seing [sic] perspective art is nothing without geometry, they are both bound together, that the workman may be able to aide and help himselfe therewith. And forasmuch as the hand cannot effect the understanding of the mind, I shall not please thereby such as are curious, yet at least I shall help yong beginners that know little or nothing thereof. This second book of architecture made by Sebastian Serly, entreating of perspective, touching the superficies, translated out of Itallian into Dutch, and out of Dutch into English, ...</title>
                  <title>Tutte l'opere d'architettura. Book 2. English</title>
                  <author>Serlio, Sebastiano, 1475-1554.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p. [24] leaves of plates   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by M[ary]. S[immons]. for Thomas Jenner at the south-entrance of the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of book 2 of: Tutte l'opere d'architettura.</note>
                  <note>Sebastian Serly = Sebastiano Serlio.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from Wing CD.</note>
                  <note>Caption title on p. 1: The second book treating of perspective: ... .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Architecture --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:39210:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39210:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A <hi>BOOK</hi> OF Perſpective &amp; Geometry, BEING The ABC, and firſt degree of all good <hi>ART. THE</hi> Learning of which comprehendeth in it many Notable Arts, need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and neceſſary for every Artificer and Workman. <hi>For as no</hi> Perſpective <hi>Workman can make any Work without</hi> Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecture, <hi>ſo neither can the</hi> Architecture <hi>without</hi> Perſpective. WHICH PERSPECTIVE <hi>IS</hi> Inſpection or looking into by ſhortning of the ſight, making it to ſhew further then in effect it is. Which Subtill and Ingenious Art, being difficult and troubleſome to be ſet down in writing, and eſpecially the body or modell of things which are drawn out of the ground. For it is an Art which cannot be ſo well expreſſed by figures or writings; as by under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhewing, which is done ſeverally, beginning with ſmall things and ſo proceeding to greater, till the full Art be perfectly ſhewed. <hi>In which is ſhewed in figures and by reaſon, as much of Perſpective Art, that if the Workman will, be may declare his conceit or purpoſe by Reaſons and Figures.</hi> And ſeing <hi>Perſpective</hi> Art is nothing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Geometry,</hi> they are both bound together, that the Workman may be able to aide and help himſelfe therewith. AND Foraſmuch as the hand cannot effect the underſtanding of the mind, I ſhall not pleaſe thereby ſuch as are curious, yet at leaſt I ſhall help yong beginners that know little or nothing thereof.</p>
            <p>This Second Book of Architecture made by SEBASTIAN SERLY, entreating of Perſpective, touching the Superficies, Tranſlated out of <hi>Itallian</hi> into <hi>Dutch,</hi> and out of <hi>Dutch</hi> into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> for the benifit of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Infelix qui pauca ſapit, ſpernitque doceri.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>M. S.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Jenner</hi> at the South-entrance of the Royall Exchange. 1657.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:39210:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:39210:2"/>
            <head>THE SECOND BOOK Treating of PERSPECTIVE: IN <hi>Which is ſhewed in Figures and by reaſon, as much of Perſpective Art; that if the Workeman will, he may declare is conceit or purpoſe by Reaſons and Figures.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FIRST, To the end that men by ſmall mattere may attaine to greater, therefore I will begin to ſhew how to ſhorten a four-corner'd thing, from whence all the reſt ſhall be derived. Then the Baſe of this four-ſquare thing, ſhall be A G, and the height of the Horiſon (as I ſaid before) ſhall be imagined according to the ſight, and that ſhall be P, whereunto all the lines do run, as the lines of the ſides A P and G P, then at the one end of the Quadrant you muſt ſet a Perpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicular line, which is G H, which done, then draw the Baſe A G K long enough, and then out of the Horiſon draw a Paralell or an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quidiſtant line from the Baſe, as far as you will that the eye or ſight ſhall ſtand from that which you will look on; for how much the more you will have the four ſquare thing to ſeem ſhorter, ſo much further you muſt goe with your ſight I from H to behold the four-ſquare thing. And then, taking H I for the diſtance, from the point I to the corner A draw a line, and where the line cutteth through the Perpendicular line H G, that is on B, there the termination of the ſhortning of the four ſquare thing ſhall be, as you may ſee in the figure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. But if you will make more four ſquares one above the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, upon the ſame Horiſon or poynt; then you muſt draw another lien from the ſhortning point of the four-ſquare or Quadrant, to the letter I, and where it cutteth through the Perpedicular line afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:39210:3"/>that is at C, there the ſecond Quadrant ſhall be cut off, and in like ſort you muſt draw another line to the point of the diſtance; and where it toucheth the Lead, or Perpendicular line, that is on D, you ſhall make the third Quadrant, the ſame may be done witn E, and ſo you muſt go untill you come juſt under the Horiſon.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The Rule aforeſaid is the perfecteſt, and you may prove it by the line G H, which is called the line of the Quadrant; but becauſe it is cumbred with a great number of lines, and ſo more tedious, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the enſuing Rule ſhall be ſhorter, and eaſier to be done then the other: for when the Baſe A G is drawn, and the two ſide lines make a Triangle A P G, then you muſt draw the paralells of the Baſe and of the Horiſon long enough; and as far as you will ſtand from the work to ſee it, ſo far you muſt ſet the Perpendiculars I K from the poynt G, then you muſt draw a line from the point I to the point A, and where it cutteth through the line G P, there ſhall be the termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the firſt ſhortned Quadrant; and if you will place more Quadrants upwards from that Quadrant, you muſt doe as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: and although there are other ways to ſhorten a Quadrant, yet will I follow this Order, as being the ſhorteſt and eaſieſt to be ſet down in writing.</p>
            <p n="3">3 A Man muſt alſo uſe himſelfe unto divers diſtances and grounds, and therefore you muſt make the ground following, which is of three Quadrants high, in this manner. Firſt, you muſt draw the line A B, as long as the bredth of the work ſhall be; which line or baſe, muſt be devided into ſo many equall parts as are needfull, which being all drawn to the Horiſon or point, then you muſt place the diſtances as far as you defire, according to the Rule aforeſaid; for here is no place to ſet it in, although it is a length and a halfe from the Baſe, as you ſee it marked with 1 ½, which Baſe, becauſe it is of four parts, therefore the firſt quadrant containeth ſixteen ſmall quadrants, which are found by the line B D, for where that line cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth through the four lines, which goe to the poynt, there you muſt draw the paralell over, that thereby the ſixteen quadrants may be formed: But if you will ſet other quadrants upon it, then (as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid) you muſt draw another line to the diſtance D, and where that cutteth through the other lines that reach to the poynt, that ſhall be the termination of the ſecond quadrant, containing in it alſo four times four quadrants: The like muſt be underſtood of the third quadrant (and more beſides if need be.) But you muſt alſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that the lines marked D run all the diſtances, as is taught befor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <figure/>
            <figure/>
            <p n="5">5 This figure is a quadrant, containing in it a Root or an other quadrant, which with the poynts thereof toucheth the ſides of the uttermoſt quadrant; whereby it is but halfe ſo great as the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt quadrant, as I have taught you in the firſt Book of Geometry, and the manner to make this, is thus: Firſt, you muſt make a qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drant (as you are taught before) with his diſtances; and in this quadrant you muſt draw two Diagonall lines, and alſo the right croſſe lines, whereby you may eaſily find the Root, as you ſee it in the 5 figure. In this ſort you may make the Roots in the other qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drants before ſet down, that is, to draw Diagonall and croſſe lines in them without taking other diſtances.</p>
            <p n="6">6 In this figure there is a croſſe ſhewed (to make it) you muſt devide the loweſt line or Baſe of the quadrant in five parts; of the which five parts, one part is the bredth of the croſſe: which bred<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h being drawn to the poynts, the Diagonall will ſhew you the Paralell lines of the croſſe, to uſe where need is.</p>
            <p n="7">7 The eight poynted figure you may ſee in Perſpective works in divers formes, which formes are all difficult enough: but that I may ſeek the eaſieſt way ſo near as I can in this my writing; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I have ſet down the manner thereof hereunto annexed, which is very eaſie, and that is thus: The quadrant being made in ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, you muſt devide the Baſe into ten-equall parts, and on either ſide you ſhall leave three parts, and in the middle four parts, then the two lines being drawn to the Horiſon, you ſhall find the termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the Paralell lines, by the Diagonall lines, whereby you may cloſe up the eight corners, as you may ſee in the 7 figure.</p>
            <p n="8">8 The ſhorteſt way to place this ſix cornerd quadrant, in Perſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive works, is thus: When the quadrant according to the Rule aforeſaid, is placed in ſhortning, then you muſt make four equall parts of the Baſis, whereof two ſhall be in the middle, and on each ſide you muſt leave one, and then draw the lines upwards to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon or poynts; then you muſt draw the Diagonall lines, and in the middle where they meet together, you muſt draw a Paralell line clean through, by the which you ſhall ſinde all the poynts to make this ſix cornerd figure.</p>
            <p n="9">9 Now I have ſhewed you how you ſhall make ſimple or plaine Perſpective works of four corners, of ſix corners, and eight ſquare corners. Now I will ſhew, now you ſhall make them double, that is, that every ſimple figure ſhall have his band. When you have made a plaine Superficies of ſix poynts, according to the Rule afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; then as much as you will have the band or faſe to be in bredth, that you muſt draw upon the Baſe, and draw that alſo up to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon; and where the Diagonall lines cut through it, there you
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:39210:5"/>muſt draw Paralell lines both under and above; and then draw two Diagonall lines more, out of the four innermoſt poynts or corners of the ſix cornerd Superficies, and ſo you ſhall find your terminations to ſhut or cloſe up your ſmalleſt ſix poynts or cornerd Superficies. Which ſecond Diagonall, Paralell, and Horiſontall lines are all drawn with pricks, for a difference from the firſt lines, that you may know them one from another.</p>
            <p n="10">10 The like muſt be done with the eight cornerd Superficies or Perſpective work, for when the ſame is made within a fourſquare, making the Compaſſe of what bredth you will, according to the rule aforeſaid; then out of every poynt or corner of the eight ſquare, a ſmall line being drawn to the Center, you ſhall find the termination to ſhut up the innermoſt eight-ſquare; and then, when from poynt to poynt the lines are drawn, then one ſquare or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe is full made. This eight ſquare forme may be changed into a round, touching the middle on either ſide, or elſe without over the poynts for corners; a good workman may eaſily draw a Circular ſhortning round line with his hand.</p>
            <p n="11">11 Although I have ſaid before that a man may make a round Circle about an eight-ſquare, yet for more ſecurity you may by this way attaine to a more perfection therein; for that the more poynts or ſides the Circular forme hath, the round Compaſſe or Circle will be the fuller. But to make this Figure, it is neceſſary to make halfe a Circle under the Baſes, and to devide the Circumference into as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny parts as you will, ſo that they be even; in this forme the halfe Circle is divided into eight parts, ſo that the whole Circle muſt be ſixteen parts; which being done, you muſt ſet Perpendicular lines in all the parts of the Circumference, as far as to the Baſes of the ſhortned quadrant, theſe parts being elevated to the Horiſon, and two Diagonall lines drawn in the quadrant, they by cutting through the Horiſontall or Radicall lines, will ſhew you the Paralell lines. Then if you will draw a little Diagonall line, beginning at the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle poynt of the Baſe, from the one ſide unto the other, and ſo from the one poynt unto the other upwards going over the poynts, then the formes will be cloſed, as you ſee them here; whereby it will be eaſie for you to draw a round forme with your hand, for it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to be done with a Compaſſe to make it ſhorten well. This 11 figure you muſt be expert in, and you muſt alſo underſtand it well, and ſo you muſt thoſe that I have before ſet down, before you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed further; for they will ſerve you for many pieces of work here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after enſuing, as you ſhall both ſee and find to be true.</p>
            <figure/>
            <figure/>
            <figure/>
            <p>But, friendly Reader, you muſt not be weary to be long in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this Figure, or in making it oftentimes, untill you can doe it perfectly and underſtand it well; for I am ſure and certaine, that it will be very hard unto many men, yet without this you cannot doe much; and he that can do it well, ſhall eaſily underſtand and make all the the things hereafter enſuing.</p>
            <p n="13">13 It falleth out many times that a workman will ſhew a Houſe both without and within, which to doe, he muſt place the ground in Perſpective forme, that he may the ſurer and better draw that up which he will have ſeen, and to leave the reſt on the ground; if then you will place a foundation in Perſpective manner, to make it well, you muſt firſt ſet it on a flat forme, that out of that you may draw it into a Perſpective forme.</p>
            <p>To doe this, I have ſet down a kind of open Building, that a man may the eaſier conceive it for a beginning, for when a man can doe this well, he may after that place many other and harder things in Perſpective forme. I need not to take any great paines to write or ſhew how this ſhortning ſhould be done, becauſe it is ſo eaſily and ſo openly placed in the figure that a man may preſently conceive it: for that leading all the lines that goe from the corners and outſides of the flat ground to the Baſe, which you will make in the ſhortning; and the ſame being drawn up to the Horiſon, together with the imagination of the diſtances; then you may ſhut or cloſe up the ſhortning four ſquare. Then you muſt draw the Diagonall lines therein, through drawing the Paralell lines, preſently you ſhall find the way how to forme the Columns and Pilaſters; ſo that it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to faile therein; and eſpecially for thoſe that doe well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and underſtand that which I have ſet down before.</p>
            <p n="14">14 This figure following is ſomewhat harder then that before, but when you goe from the ſmalleſt to the greateſt, you conceive things the eaſier, and eſpecially he that will learne this Art; he muſt not leave nor refuſe to exerciſe any of the Figures before ſet down, but muſt uſe all the diligence he can to be perfect in them all, and be muſt alſo take a pleaſure to doe them all, otherwiſe he that will omit now one, and then another, becauſe he can hardly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand or conceive them (although I labour and ſtrive at all times in ſetting down theſe Rules to ſhew all difficulties) ſhall little profit himſelfe in this Art. The manner how to place this ground in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective forme, is eaſily conceived, without any other Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: for you muſt follow the manner or operation of the figure before ſet down, with this Advertiſement, That the two Diagonall lines evermore direct the work, together with the Horiſontall lines: and although a man may ſhew many formes of grounds that are to be placed in ſhortning, yet theſe two ſhall ſuffice for this time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I have other things to entreat off: for a ſkilfull workman, by the help of theſe, may forme others for his purpoſe; and ſuch as be ſhall have occaſion to uſe. And if he will erect any piece of work
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:39210:8"/>for a ſhew he muſt neceſſarily firſt meaſure the Orthography with the ſame meaſure that he meaſureth the ground withall, and then place it in a ſhortning manner, as when time ſerveth, ſhall be ſhewed.</p>
            <p n="15">15 Touching the grounds and other Superficies of divers forms, I think I have ſufficiently ſpoken Now I will ſpeak of Bodies which are drawn up out of the ground: And firſt, you know that I have taught before, how you ſhould frame an eight-ſquare forme plainly in it ſelfe; and then, I have ſhewed how you ſhould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe this Figure about, with a border or edge: but if a workman will ſhew an eight-ſquare Figure in Perſpective wiſe, as a Well; then he muſt firſt make the ground, as he is taught before, as high as he will, that the ſaid Well ſhall ſtand elevsted above the ground or foot thereof: there he muſt make the ſame forme once againe, drawing it to the ſame Horiſon; then from all the uppermoſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners or poynts to the loweſt, you muſt draw Perpendicular lines as well from the innermoſt figures, as from the uttermoſt, whereby the through cutting eight ſquare bodies will be formed, as you may ſee in the 15 Figure.</p>
            <p n="16">16 I have ſpoken before of the open frame of a Well with eight poynts or corners, which is neceſſary to be learned, how to make it, before you make the ſolid body thereof, as this Figure 16 ſheweth, which is the ſame that is before ſhewed, both forme and meaſure, but all the lines which cannot outwardly be ſeen, are hidden; and there is as much difference between an open body and a ſolid, as there is between the modell of a mans body, that is nothing but bones without fleſh and ſkin; and a living body of a man covered over with fleſh (although it is hidden under it.) And as thoſe Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are much perfecter that have ſeen, and perfectly beheld right Anatomies, then others that onely content themſelves with the outward bare ſhew of the Superficies, ſo it is with Perſpective works; for they that well underſtand and perfectly bear in minde the bidden lines, they ſhall better underſtand the Art then others, that content themſelves only with the ſhew of outward Superficies. It is very true, that when a man hath ſufficiently experimented, practiſed, and beareth in his mind theſe inward hidden lines, then helping himſelfe with the principall, he may make many perfect things, without uſing all this labour.</p>
            <figure/>
            <figure/>
            <figure/>
            <p>But if any man that deſireth to learn this Art, will at the firſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand theſe figures, as ſome bluntly will take upon him to do it. I believe certainely, he will be put to an <hi>non plus,</hi> and deceive him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; but if by learning all the former things, he proceedeth unto theſe as well in Geometry as in Perſpective Art: Then, I ſay, he is of a very groſſe underſtanding, if he cannot underſtand or conceive theſe figures, or the figures that hereafter follow.</p>
            <p>Theſe three figures, to ſpeak truth, are but Superficies; neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, if you draw Perpendicular lines from all the terminations, as well within as without: then you ſhall have a through cutting or open body, and the innermoſt lines covered, then they will be a Maſſy body: And wonder not, gentle Reader, nor let it be ſtrange unto you, though I doe ſometimes make a long diſcourſe of ſome things, for (as I ſaid before) they are not onely learned by many words and great paines, but it is alſo neceſſary that they were ſhewed unto ſome men plainly by drawing them before them, that they may the better conceive them.</p>
            <p n="18">18 The moſt part of great Rivers or water-falls that fall down from high Hills or Mountains, by means of tempeſts with great force and power, when they enter into a Valley, then ſometimes they run out of their Channell, and ſo much ground as they then uſurp upon the one ſide, ſo much they looſe againe one the other ſide; and ſo doth Perſpective work in cornerd things, for that as much as a man loſeth of the poynt or corner whereon he looketh, ſo much greater the other poynt or comer ſheweth that ſtandeth out, which is ſhewed in the figures 18, hereunto annexed.</p>
            <p>The Reader muſt then mark, that the ſquare in the middle ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth the thickneſſe of a foure-ſquare Columne or Pillar, and the border that is without and goeth about it, ſignifieth the thickneſſe or bearing out of the Baſes and the Capitall. The figure under this platforme is the Baſe, and the uppermoſt figure is the Capitall; the manner how to ſhorten them I will ſhew you, You muſt make the Pillar flat before without thickneſſe, and upon it you ſhall forme the Baſes and Capitall, making the projecture or bearing out there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of on either ſide alike, but you muſt draw them lightly as the pricks herein ſet down doe ſhew you: then draw the ſide of the Pillar which you will have ſeen towards the Horiſon; and having found how thick the decreaſing or ſhortning ſide muſt be, by the rules that are ſhewed in the firſt part of Perſpective work, ſo you ſhall have the the ſhortning ground of the Pillar, wherein you muſt light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly draw the two Diagonall lines long enough through, and from the Baſes below, which is ſeen in the ſhortning; you muſt draw a line towards the Horiſon, which you ſhall alſo let goe down or ſink ſo far, till it reacheth beneath the Diagonall lines, and there ſhall be the terminations of the ſhortning Baſes: and thus you ſee that the Perſpectiveneſſe taketh ſomewhat off from them, that is, the ſpace
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:39210:11"/>between the poynts, and the full back line; then from the termina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to the other uttermoſt poynt of the Baſes, you muſt draw a Paralell line under the ground of the Pillars, ſo long that it may touch the Diagonall lines, and there you ſhall find that which is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of from the Baſes on the one ſide, and given to them on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, and the projecture of the Baſes ſheweth, that the one poynt is draw inwards, and the other cometh further out, then the uppermoſt line of the Baſes being alſo to the Horiſon; then upon the ſhortning ſide by a line you ſhall find the third part of the Baſes below, and that which is here ſpoken of the Baſes, you muſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the ſame alſo of the Capitalls.</p>
            <p n="19">19 Theſe other three Figures are the ſame which are ſhewed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; the firſt were hollow, but theſe are perfect and ſolid with all their members, and although that in the figures before I have not ſhewed how you ſhould forme and frame theſe members, which in truth would be a very confuſed and troubleſome thing to ſet down in writing; therefore I have onely ſhewed the firſt terminations, that a man may keep them well in his memory, and in theſe preſent Figures I have ſhewed how they ſhew in a mans ſight, that you may ſee the effect that they work: but from henceforward becauſe (as I ſaid before) it is a troubleſome thing, I will make another forme of them with all their members by dark lines; and then (according to my ability) I will ſet down the manner how to find the termina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the members one after another, for all of them grow a little one over, or more then the other.</p>
            <p>But you muſt conſider, that theſe Baſes and Capitalls on the one ſide give in ward, and on the other ſide beareth out, which you muſt well remember, that you may firſt be well inſtructed herein touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that which you will make. For it is true, that the Theorick conſiſteth in the underſtanding; but experience is gotten by pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe and right uſe or handling: Therefore the moſt notable Painter <hi>Leonardus Vinci,</hi> was never pleaſed nor ſatisfied with any thing that he made, bringing but little work to perfection, ſaying, the cauſe thereof was that his hand could not effect the underſtanding of his mind: And for my part, if I ſhould doe as he did, I ſhould not, neither would I ſuffer any of my works to come forth: for (to ſay the truth) whatſoever I make or write, it pleaſeth me not, but (as I ſaid in the beginning of my work) that I had rather exerciſe in work that ſmall talent, which it hath pleaſed God to beſtow upon me, then ſuffer it to lie and rot under the earth without any fruit; and although I ſhall not pleaſe thereby ſuch as are curious, to ſet down the ground and perfection of all things, yet at leaſt I ſhall help yong beginners that know little or nothing thereof, which hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways been my intent.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>And firſt, You muſt frame this Baſe with all the members, and with the right Projecture thereof, to be without any ſhortning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, yet you muſt draw it lightly with a piece of Lead, or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing, as it is ſhewed unto you in the Figure with pricks; then in the ground or foot of the Pillar you muſt draw the two Diago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall lines long enough out, and thereby (as I ſaid before) you ſhall find the diminiſhing and the increaſing of the particuler parts of the creſts of the ſaid Baſe, whereas the undermoſt line or foot of the creſts of the Baſe, bear much more broader and longer then thoſe that are marked with the pricks; then at each corner of the Creaſt of the Baſe you muſt draw an upright line almoſt as high as the firſt creaſt of the Baſe (although I have done it) but upon the uttermoſt poynt not to comber the work within: then you muſt draw the uppermoſt corners of the firſt Creaſt with pricks alſo, toward the Horiſon, which downwards will touch againſt the two upright lines; and there ſhall be the terminations to cloſe or ſhut up the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond great Creaſt with a full black line: then draw another black line from the innermoſt point of the Creaſt upwards to the Horiſon, and there the ſhortning Creaſt ſhall be cloſed.</p>
            <p>And as this Creaſt or Plinthus is cloſed and drawn on all ſides with black lines, ſo you muſt doe with all the other lines of the Baſe, for when from the uppermoſt corner of the firſt marked Baſe you draw a helding line to the innermoſt corner of the greateſt Creaſt with the black lines, by it you ſhall lightly find the terminations of all the parts or members, drawing the corners of the firſt Baſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Horiſon. And when you have formed all the innermoſt corners of the Baſes, by the Horiſentall line you may eaſily doe the ſecond, and by the Paralell lines the uttermoſt of all; although by the lines of the diſtances, you may bring the ſaid corners ſomewhat nearer, as you may ſee by the Diagonall lines. But at this time I will not ſpeak of that difficult or hard work, for he that hath any under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, may herewith help himſelfe.</p>
            <p>That which is here ſaid of the Baſes, you muſt alſo underſtand of the Cornices, onely that every thing is contrary; and where you ſet Perpendicular lines below, which cut through the Horiſentall or Radiall lines, ſo you muſt alſo fall above the Lead lines or Catheten upon the Horiſentall lines, as you may better ſee it and learne it in the Figure, then it can be expreſſed by words: and you muſt not be afraid or abaſhed, although at firſt you cannot conceive it, for that by practiſing you ſhall in time find it; for it is not ſaid that a man ſhall or can learne all things at once in one day: by this Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:39210:13"/>you may make all Cornices, be they higher or lower, harder or eaſier, always drawing every member and part towards the Horiſon, as it ſhould be done.</p>
            <p n="21">21 Although there are divers manners and wayes to place Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumns one behind the other, ſtanding upon one ground in Perſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive wiſe, thereby to make Portals, Galleries, and other things, yet this hereunto annexed is the eaſieſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt, You muſt make a Pavement with a quantity of four cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerd Quadrants, as it is alſo ſhewed in the beginning of this Book, which may be made of ſuch bredth, as you will: Say that theſe foure-ſquare ſtones are two foot broad, which ſhall be the thickneſs of a Pillar: between the two firſt Pillars beneath in the bredth, there ſhall be eight ſequare ſtones, and the height of the Pillars made of what quantity you will; and they being raiſed toward the Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, then you muſt draw two ſeverall lines over both the Pillars, and then out of the middle of the firſt line you muſt make two halfe Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles above upon the flat ſide before, and devide them in as many parts as you will; which parts ſhall be drawn to the Center of the halfe Circle, ſtanding in the uppermoſt line: then out of the middle of the two ſeverall lines you muſt draw the leſſe halfe Circle, and all terminations of the flat Arch being drawn to the Horiſon, then the firſt Arch or Gate is made: the other two Pillars upwards ſhall alſo ſtand eight Quadrants diſtant from the firſt Pillars, which will make a foure cornerd place on all ſides, containing 64 ſquare ſtones; and you muſt doe with this Gate as you did with the firſt, onely (when they are all of one wideneſſe as theſe are) you need not devide the Arches againe, for the Horiſentall lines of the ſtones of the firſt Arch will ſhew you the terminations of all the other Arches, and alſo how long the Gallery muſt be, and how many Arches it muſt containe. I have placed no Arches here in the ſides, becauſe I would not cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber you too much at this time; but I will ſpeak thereof hereafter particularly.</p>
            <p>The two Doors on each ſide are both partly covered with the Pillars, but the wideneſſe of them is of four Quadrants, beſides that from the corner of the Doors to the Pillars on each ſide there is two Quadrants, as you ſee the halfe thereof; and the other halfe you muſt ſuppoſe to be behind the Pillars. The beams above the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches which bear up the Chamber above, you may gueſſe, although I write not particularly thereof: I have not likewiſe ſet the Baſes nor the Capitalls upon theſe Pillars, becauſe they ſhould not darken them too much; but in another place I will alſo entreat thereof.</p>
            <figure/>
            <figure/>
            <figure/>
            <p>Theſe Diagonall lines will not onely ſhew you the thickneſſe of the firſt or foremoſt Pillars when they ſhorten, but alſo the thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the two other Pillars which ſtand inward, which are all marked with pricks (and as I have likewiſe ſaid before) that which is here ſaid of the Baſes of the Pillars, the ſame alſo muſt be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood upward of the Capitalls: touching the thickneſſe of the Bowes or Arches underneath, I have ſhewed in the Figure before, how you muſt place the Center in the middle of the foure croſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynt lines, to draw the halfe Circumference: The four-ſquare or Quadrant above, is as great as that below on the ground; I need not ſhew how you ſhall make it, for you ſee it plain enough in the Figure.</p>
            <p n="23">23 This Figure is like the former, onely that the members of the Baſes and Capitalls are added thereunto, thereby to make it more perfect unto you, and to ſhew you how a thing will ſtand when it is full made and finiſhed, although I have ſhewed it before; neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, when a man is perfect therein, then he may by practiſe help himſelfe well enough without all this labour; uſing diſcretion and bearing in memory that which he hath imprinted in his mind: For in truth, by this means (I mean the ground) a man may by practiſe make many things, which if they be made with diſcretion, and by a workman will alwayes beautifie the work, as theſe bowes or Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches doe, which under are devided with Quadrants, as you may ſee them. There are, as you know, firſt two Centers to forme the Arch underneath, now a wiſe workman muſt not alwayes ſeek for the perfection of the edge of theſe Quadrants; but for example, Say that the Arch underneath is devided into eight parts, whereof ſix ſhall be for the Quadrant, and two parts for the edge or border that runneth about it: now you muſt devide the ſpace between the one Center and the other, alſo in eight parts, but they muſt ſhorten or leſſen a little, that is, the neather part againſt the upper; and then the Compaſſe being ſet ſomewhat lower, and made narrower, then you muſt draw the uppermoſt border; and then the Compaſſe being ſet a little below the nethermoſt Center, you muſt in like ſort draw the other edge or border: after, you muſt ſquare or devide the Quadrants, leaving the ſpace between both, once ſo broad again as the other, which muſt be drawn up towards the Horiſon; and as much as you will mak the quadrant ſink, you muſt alſo draw out of the laſt Center with the Compaſſe. And in this manner a man may make divers forms and compartments (but as I have ſaid) you muſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:39210:16"/>make them all with judgement, and therefore it is very convenient that a man ſhould be well inſtructed therein; for that uſing onely the princicall terminations, you muſt make the reſt by practiſe: But I am of opinion, that ſome rigorous Perſpective men will take hold of theſe mywords, (to whom I anſwer) that if they mean I have failed or done amiſſe, let them prove what difference there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween ſaying and doing.</p>
            <p n="24">24 The manner how to make a croſſe roofe of a Gallery or Houſe in Perſpective work, is alwayes very troubleſome to ſhew it unto any man; and therefore alſo, it is much more troubleſome to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it in writing for men hereafter to underſtand it. Nevertheleſſe, becauſe it is very neceſſary to be known, I will doe the beſt I can to ſhew it.</p>
            <p>Firſt, you muſt chuſe the bredth and heigth of the greateſt Arch or Bow that you deſire to make, and then by the diſtances you muſt make a perfect ſhortning quadrant, and alſo a leſſe Bow or Arch. The greateſt Arch before ſhall be devided into eight equall parts, and thoſe parts muſt be drawn towards the Horiſon to the ſmall Arch, which being done, then you muſt ſet thoſe parts of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Arch below upon the Baſe; and with the help of the Horiſentall and Diagonall lines, you may make a ſhortning Circle within the quadrant, as in the other places before you have been taught. The terminations hereof ſhall be 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, which ſhall be ſet upwards beſide the great Arch, as you may ſee it there alſo marked with 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. Without this round below I have drawn the Paralells with pricks to the wall, and where they end, there you muſt ſet all your Perpendicular lines upright, which are come out of the Paralell lines of this Circle.</p>
            <p>Then you muſt draw the terminations aforeſaid, which are placed above, along by the Perpendicular lines with lines to the Horiſon; and where the ſaid Horiſentall lines cut through the Perpendicular lines, which are drawn up from below, there you muſt make halfe a ſhortning Circle; and that which is marked on this ſide with Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, muſt alſo be underſtood to ſtand on the other, as you ſee it in the Figure.</p>
            <figure/>
            <figure/>
            <figure/>
            <p n="25">25 Having ſhewed in croſſe work on both ſides, how you ſhould place the Arches on the ſides in ſhortning manner, and drawn them up out of the ground, although that they be ſingle: now will I ſhew you a hollow Arch, and the manner how to ſhorten it: But before I proceed thereunto (for it is very comberſome and difficult) firſt I will ſhew you the Pilaiſters that ſhould carry the ſaid Arches, which Pilaiſters ſtand ſo plainly in the Figure that I ſhall not need to take much paines to write of them. In this Figure I have not made the firſt Arch, that I might not darken the ſight of the Arches on the ſides, which Arches on the ſides, I have alſo but marked how they ſhall ſtand, and are alwayes drawn out of the four-ſquare quadrant, as you ſee by the order of the four-ſquare quadrant, but the hinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Arch which ſtandeth not in the way, I have drawn fully, and and placed it alſo in his four-ſquare.</p>
            <p>Above in the top or roofe, I have made the round forme, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of you may make a Kettle or Tribunall; and you may alſo make it thus, when it is ſo me what ſunk. Touching the four Pilaiſters, they (as I have taught before) are found by the Diagonall lines coming from the poynt of the diſtances, and alſo that each Pilaiſter is three cornerd, ſtanding like a three cornerd hook, and on each end (the Arch reſteth, whereof there ſhall be foure) two Arches before, and two on the ſides, ſo that the roofe will be right four-ſquare, wherein you may make croſſe work or other manner of Roofe work. And if you will make other kindes of works by the ſame, you muſt alwayes follow this Rule: Item, where you cannot well underſtand my writing, you muſt help your ſelves with the Figures, which Figure alſo ſtandeth open, ſo that with a little labour, a man may eaſily conceive it altogether, although there were nothing ſpoken of it.</p>
            <p n="26">26 Now you ſee, what way you muſt follow to place Arches on the ſides in ſhortning manner: And firſt, you muſt think upon the third former manner Superficies, wherein I have ſufficiently ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you the manner how to frame a round body; but in this Figure I will ſhew it more perfectly. Wherefore a man muſt imagine that the round Body lying below in his four-ſquare is made, and ſhall ſerve for the two Bowes on the ſides. This Body then being made (as I have ſhewed before) and as you ſee it better now, you muſt firſt ſet it, where the Arches begin above the Horiſon. And the ſame Perpendicular lines which ſtand corner-wiſe from the middle of the four cornerd body, muſt be ſet like Paralell lines on the right and left ſides upwards from the two Arches, there (as it is aforeſaid) to direct the Horiſentall lines, as you may ſee't it plainly in the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure. But you muſt underſtand, that the two croſſes below in this Body, are the two Centers to draw the ſtones of the Arches both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove and below, they alſo ſignifie the Centers of the Bowes upon the Horiſentall lines within the Arches.</p>
            <p>You muſt alſo underſtand, that the black lines doe forme the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference without, and the pricks or thin lin as betoken the forme
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:39210:20"/>within, which is covered in the Arches; ſo that the Arches do ſhew through to be made of pieces, of the which pieces a man may learne to make divers Compartments underneath in the Arch. Now when a man can make this Arch well, then he ſhall not need ſtill to take all this labour, but by two principall lines helping himſelfe with pricks, he may frame the Arch; and eſpecially, becauſe that the Arch which ſhould come before, covereth or bideth a great part of the Arches on both ſides; which Arch I have not made here, that I might not darken or ſhadow the other ſhortning Arch. Neither need I write any thing of the Circumferences above in the top or Roofe, (nor the eight corners within) for that in the next Figure you ſhall ſee them; neither will I ſpeak any thing of the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences in the ground, for they are made (as I have taught you heretofore of all others) and of the round body below (of the which there hath been more ſaid) a man may make many other things which are not here to be ſpoken of.</p>
            <p n="27">27 To place Pillars with their Arches upon grounds or plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes, I think there is ſufficient ſpoken before; and whatſoever I have ſpoken of foure-ſquare Pillars, is alſo to be underſtood of round Columns, for that a man muſt take all round things, out of four-ſquare things, as well the Spira of the Baſe, as the round of the Capitall. He that can make all the Figures aforeſaid perfectly, and particularly this laſt body, ſhall help himſelfe well, and not onely to doe the like things, but alſo many more. If I ſhould in this ſmall Treatiſe ſhew all that I could ſet down, it would make a moſt great Volumn; and peradventure I ſhould want time to ſet forth the reſt of my Book, which I have already promiſed: for there are many things that belong to Building, which need not to be ſet down in Perſpective work.</p>
            <p>Let us now begin to-raiſe the Building here ſet down out of the ground, which before, and on the ſide is ſeen, as I promiſed before to ſhew you.</p>
            <p>The ſhorteſt and ſureſt way is, to make a ground with many qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drants; and imagine that it is mere with the Foot, with the Elle, or other meaſure: but let us now take every quadrant for two foot, and as before there are foure quadrants from one Pillar to the other, and the Pillar alſo containeth a quadran, there ſhall alſo be foure quadrants upward in the length from one Pillar the other, as you may ſee it altogether in the Figure.</p>
            <p>The Pillars then being ſet of ſuch height as you deſire, then the the Arches upon them muſt be made; and the manner how to make them, you may expreſly ſee in the Figure. And although you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee the Arches that are behind them, yet I have made them here that you may ſee their terminations; they are in ſome places drawn with full black lines, and in ſome places with pricks.</p>
            <figure/>
            <figure/>
            <figure/>
            <p>I have here made no Baſes nor Capitalls, that the other things might not be confounded: but you muſt underſtand that they muſt be placed in the work, as is ſufficiently before ſhewed. And by this Rule you may draw divers Buildings out of the ground, as in the Figure is ſhewed in divers formes. The Centers of the Arches you ſee them marked, ſtanding all upon one Horiſentall line.</p>
            <p n="28">28 Now I have ſhewed the manner how to make a Gallery with Arches and Pillars, with other things thereunto belonging; now by an eaſier way I will ſhew ſome forme of Houſes that are to be built out of the ground. You muſt make a ground or foot work with qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drants reaching long enough upwards, which quadrants muſt each of them be reckoned at two foot ſquare.</p>
            <p>And firſt, at the entry of the Houſe there ſhall be a door of five foot broad, for that it containeth two quadrants and a halfe in the ſhortning: and the height thereof ſhall be of ten foot, becauſe it is five quadrants high: Her Pilaiſters or Antipagmentum ſhall be a foot broad, becauſe they containe a halfe ſhortning quadrant; the Friſe ſhall alſo containe as much: and the Cornice ſhall containe ſo much leſſe, as the under part thereof bearing over containeth, and ſhall be made according to the Rule aforeſhewed. Touching the part jetting over the door, the Mogdilions or Mutiles, ſhall ſtand right above Pilaiſters or Antipagmentum of the door. And that little door upon the jetting, ſhall ſtand right in the middle above the loweſt door, and ſhall be two foot broad. In the other corner of of this firſt Houſe, there ſhall be another door, the wideneſſe thereof ſhall be ſix foot; you may make it round or ſquare above as you will. But why doe I ſpend my time to ſet down all theſe meaſures, which you may ſo plainly ſee in the Figure; onely it is neceſſary to warn ſuch as are ſtudious herein, that what work ſoever a man rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth out of the ground, conſiſteth in three principall things, that is, in length, bredth, and height. The length is of certaine Houſes or Rooms, containing a certaine number of feet. The bredth conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of Windows, Doors, Gates, Shops, and ſuch like things. The height conſiſteth of Ports, Windows, Jettings, Cornices, Columns, Roofs, and ſuch like things. But there is yet another, that is, of the thickneſſe of the Walls, Pillars, Columns, and Pilaiſters: The length is taken from the ſhortning quadrants, and from thence alſo you take the bredth. But the height is taken out of the bredth in the quadrants, which bredth muſt be taken from the quadran or halfe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:39210:23"/>quadran, which toucheth it on the hithermoſt ſide as it ſtandeth: as alſo from the hithermoſt door, which is ten foot high, there you muſt take the meaſure from the quadrans, which come to the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lells on the nethermoſt corner or poynt of the door; for if there you take five quadrans in bredth, it ſhall be the height within the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagementum. And that which I have ſaid of theſe doors, you muſt alſo underſtand of all the other things: The thickneſſe of the Wall is two foot, for you ſee it containeth a quadrant. The bearing over of the ſecond Houſe is of ſix foot, meaſured upon the ground: the like alſo the bearing over or jetting of the firſt Houſe containeth. To conclude all things, as I have ſaid, riſing out of the ground on all ſides, I have ſet no Cornices, nor any other ornaments in this Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, that you may the eaſier underſtand it; but a man of ripe judgement and underſtanding knowing the terminations, can by by his own invention help himſelfe to make faire Buildings. And for that I may not ſpend to much time herein, I will make others to give you more light therein.</p>
            <p n="29">29 The Stayres, degrees or goings up, are very neceſſary in Buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, and therefore I will ſhew divers kinds thereof, and firſt I will begin with the eaſieſt. According to common cuſtome a ſtayre or ſtep is about half a foot high, and about a foot broad upon the ſtep; then let the ſquare ſtones of this ground be a foot ſquare, therewith we will make a paire of ſtayres of five foot high, and three foot broad: at the foot of the ground we will take the meaſure of the bredth, which on the right and left ſides ſhall be ſet in Perpendicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar lines on the Corners of the Stayres, which ſhall be devided into ten, as the lines A B ſhew you. Then all the parts of A B ſhall be raiſed to the Horiſon, and then you ſhall take nine quadrants up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in length: and whereas two lines are ſet up cutting through the Horiſentall lines of A B, there the Corners D C of the upper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſteps ſhall be, containing a four-ſquare of the three quadrants on each ſide. From the hithermoſt poynts of the ſame upper ſteps, you ſhall draw two helding lines to the loweſt ſteps; againſt the which the Horiſentall and the Perpendicular lines of the quadrant ſhall come together and ſhut up the Stayres.</p>
            <p>Theſe Stayres are ſhortned on the one ſide, and the other is plain or profill, and containeth a ſtep leſſe in the heigth, which maketh four foot and a halfe; it is alſo three foot broad, as it is marked un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it on the ground. By this Rule you may make Stayres or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees as high as you will, and make ſome reſting places in the way: alwayes taking the meaſure from the foot of the ground, as well of the ſhortning, as thoſe that are upright.</p>
            <p n="30">30 The going up being plaine or profill maketh a great ſhew, and yet are very eaſie to ſet in all places, I mean in the turning, and may ſerve for many things, ſpecially in Buildings, where a man go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up ſoftly and with eaſe, giveth the beholders a kind of pleaſure to view them, principally in common places, for that there is a go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up on either ſide, ſo that upon the one ſide men may goe up, and one the other ſide they may goe down; and although there are onely but two goings up, yet by this a man by his own invention
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:39210:23"/>may deviſe others. How theſe Stayres are made, and with what reaſon, you may by this Figure perceive them, although I ſhould ſay nothing thereof; for as it is ſaid before, the quadrants are of a foot broad, and the ſteps halfe a foot high, and ſo the bredth of the ſtep is one foot. The bredth of the Stayres is five foot, both the firſt and ſecond: The reſting gate containeth in wideneſſe three foot, and is ſix foot high; which although it ſeemeth to be ſhut, and a ſmall door opening in it; yet it may be made whole, open, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe cloſed. The two ſides above the three ſteps are five foot broad, although here it is but one foot, becauſe of the narrowneſſe of the Paper. The Perpendicular lines on the ſides, ſignifie leaning places, and they ſhould ſerve well alſo to the ſteps, but leaſt they ſhould comber the work, I have left them out.</p>
            <p n="31">31 Amongſt other things which ſhew well in Perſpective work, I find that goings up or Stayres are very ſeemly, and that the oftner that they turne, the better they doe ſhew; therefore I have made theſe two goings up turning, which ſtand in profill, yet you ſee the ground and the ſteps. This firſt going up is ſix foot high, and three foot broad, as you may ſee it marked in the grounds with pricks: the reſting place between the firſt and ſecound going up, is two foure ſquares long, which is neceſſary, becauſe of the turning. At the end thereof you find a Portall, the door thereof is two foot wide, the Antipagmentum is halfe a foot on either ſide, ſo that the place is three foot full. The Perpendicular lines on the right ſide of the plaine, ſignifie certain leanings, which may be made of Iron, Wood, or Stone; the like may be made along the Stayres both upward and downward, ſetting a Baluſter upon every Stayre: The height of this raile or leaning, ſhall be two foot and a halfe, for ſo it is eaſie to lay a mans hand upon. How theſe Stayres are made upwards out of the ground, although it may well be ſeen by the Figure with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out declaring it: yet I will ſay ſomething thereof, to eaſe them that are ſhort of memory. The reſting gate or round door under the plaineſſe between the ſecond and the third going up, is no deeper then to the wall: Above the ſame door there ſtandeth another go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up, of four ſteps, which to make, I have ſufficiently ſhewed; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe a man ſhould continue the ground at the reſting door, to draw them up from it.</p>
            <p n="32">32 Touching the ſeverall kinds of Stayres, I am aſſured that they may partly be underſtood without deſcribing them in writing, and ſpecially the middlemoſt which goeth up on both fides; and ſo ſhall the uppermoſt alſo, becauſe it is raiſed up from the ground as well as the other, and is ſix foot broad, as you may ſee and tell it on the ground upon the plaine ſtones. The two Arches under the two goings up are each a foot in thickneſſe, whereby a going down is four foot within, and is alſo drawn out of the ground as the reſt are. The other goings up, which you ſee through the Arches; you may ſufficiently perceive by them how they are made: and ſo it is with the two of paire Staires on the left hand, for from the firſt ſteps at the reſting door, you may eaſily ſee how they are raiſed up out of the ground, and above at the end of them they have a piece of plaine
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:39210:24"/>ground to come to the other Stayres, which alſo is drawn up out of the pavement as the reſt are, that is, each ſtep halfe a foot high, and a foot broad. But it is hard to meaſure in ſo ſmall things, but it ſufficeth that hereby you may ſee the manner thereof; and when you make them great you ſhall find that they will come well enough to paſſe. Under the Stayres laſt named, there ſtandeth alſo a round door which is five foot wide: upon this ground, and on theſe Stayres a cunning Painter might place divers Figures in ſeverall formes, either ſtanding or ſitting upon the Stayres, and lying upon the ground in ſhortning manner, and that in this wiſe: You may place the Figures where you will with feet, and then take ſix feet or ſquares where on they ſtand, and that ſhall be their height, for that it is the height of a common or ordinary man: this you muſt obſerve both before and behinde, and in every place. If the Figure be upon a ſtep, then take the meaſure of that ſtep whereon it ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, and make it twelve ſteps high, which ſhall be ſix foot: And is the Figure lying, doe the like; but if it lyeth in ſhortning manner upon the ground, then you muſt take the length by the ſhortning quadrant.</p>
            <p n="33">33 I have ſhewed many kinds of goings up, but there are other kinds, and he that is not well inſtructed in the former will hardly underſtand theſe two which I have here ſet down. The firſt ſhall be winding ſtayres in four ſquare, and he that can make theſe foure-ſquare Stayres, may well make the round Stayres, for it is all one thing, ſpecially if he uſeth the Rule before ſet down of the round bodies.</p>
            <figure/>
            <figure/>
            <figure/>
            <p n="34">34 That I may not forget to ſet down all kinds of Stayres, and eſpecially ſuch as often times fall out to be made; therefore I have made theſe Stayres, whereon a man may goe up on all ſides, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the ground ſtandeth above on the right hand, but yet very ſmall. Theſe Stayres muſt be thus made: Firſt, you muſt make a foure-ſquare ſhortning body of halfe a foot high, upon this you muſt draw two Diagonall lines, and from the corner inwards there ſhall be a foot broad left on either ſide, and the terminations thereof drawn to the Horiſon, and ſo from the Diagonall lines you ſhall ſee the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the ſecond ſtep. Now I need not ſet down unto you how you ſhall find the leſning corner of the ſecond ſtep, the which is round about ſhut up with Paralell and Horiſentall lines: then up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſecond plaine you muſt draw two Diagonall lines, which do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as I ſaid before) will ſhew you the third ſtep; which alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cloſed up with lines, you ſhall alſo find the fourth and fifth, with the like Rules. This Piramides is fantaſtically framed upon them to fill up the place. Alſo I need not ſet down to what uſes theſe Stayres may ſerve, for that the halfe of them is commonly found in divers pieces of work, as the Gates of Pallaces, Churches, and other dwelling Houſes, and the aſcending up to Altars. By this way alſo you may make round Stayres, and alſo Stayres of ſix or eight cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, as by their formes I have ſhewed.</p>
            <p n="35">35 I have promiſed the ſtudious Reader by this my labour to ſhew as much of Perſpective work as I can, that he might ſhew his conceit touching Houſes or Buildings in Perſpective wiſe, meaning to ſet down ſome ſimple manners thereof, as if he ſhould forme a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle or double ground, thereupon to raiſe a body, and therewith mean to make an end. But falling from one work to another, I am en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into a Laborinth, which peradventure is to far above my reach, which cometh to paſſe by means of ſome men that have entreated me thereunto. And therefore, as I thought at this time to make an end of my ſecond Book, I begin to handle a harder matter, which Rule is onely called an outward foure-ſquare: nevertheleſſe, it is as well drawn by the Horiſon as by the diſtances, as you may ſee in the Figure, which ſheweth a right ſhortning foure-ſquare, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in it another four-ſquare, the which alſo may be formed by the diſtances without Horiſon; ſome men place the ſides of the foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſquare upon the Baſe, once ſo wide againe as before. And as you ſee two like ſides of the four-ſquare over the corner, ſo are the diſtances
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:39210:27"/>alike marked D. And as much more as you will have this foure-ſquare to ſhorten, ſo much you muſt draw the diſtances from the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon; and as much as you will that the edges of the foure-ſquare ſhall be broad, ſo many bredths muſt you draw upon the Baſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween A C twice drawn. All the terminations of this four-ſquare ſtanding above the corners goe all to the diſtances, and none to the Horiſon, but onely the four-ſquare that is ſet therein.</p>
            <p n="36">36 Now I have ſhewed, how you ſhould ſhorten a Superficies, overpoynt, or outward four-ſquare; here I will ſhew you how to imboſſe or bear out the body thereof with the ſame Horiſon and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances alſo, which body within is hollow, and you may heave it up as high as you will; but I have purpoſely left it ſomewhat low, that you might ſee the ground thereof. And by this Figure you may conceive to how many things this may ſerve; and alſo how you may increaſe or diminiſh it, according to ſkill and judgement. This ſhall ſuffice for theſe foure-ſquare modells or hollow things; but I will ſhew you how you ſhall make them with Creaſts or Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nices.</p>
            <p n="37">37 This Figure is alſo formed by the aforeſaid Horiſon, and the like diſtances as the other before, onely they ſtand a little nearer: Now to creaſt this body both above and beneath, you muſt imagine the greatneſſe of the Creaſt, and draw the ſame greatneſs both above and beneath the body; then give the Creſts above their due Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture, and from thoſe poynts you muſt let Perpendicular lines fall to the poynts or corners below, whereby you ſhall have the Proje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctives of the Baſe and top thereof, which muſt be drawn towards the Diſtances, and not towards the Horiſon. Now you ſee how the Cornices ſtand without the foure-ſquare body: but this is onely for Cornices that are made without members, not to comber you with the ſhadowing of them, for I will ſpeak of them hereafter particularly.</p>
            <p n="38">38 I ſpake before of Cornices without members, which might ſerve this hollow Quadran, and how you ſhall make the termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations thereof. Now in this Figure I ſhew you the ſaid Cornices with their members, which you may alſo make in other manner as it pleaſeth the workman, that is, to make them bigger or leſſer, as I have ſpoken of other Cornices, alwayes uſing good diſcretion and judgement to chuſe and make ſuch members therein, as may ſhew well in mens ſight. There are ſome Cornices which reach ſo far o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, that men cannot ſee the members thereof under them; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in that caſe the members are ſo to be made, that they may be ſeemly and pleaſant in mens ſight.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p n="40">40 This body hereafter following is raiſed out of the former Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure before ſet down, and is made with the ſame Horiſon; which body containeth two quadrants in length, and one quadrant in height, for the line CD is ſet in Perpendicular manner upon the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermoſt corner, whereon the other Superficies are ſet: thus then this body is of two four-ſquares, I mean two four-ſquares in length, and one four-ſquare broad and high. And this body (as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) ſhall ſerve for many things: But if you will have more cubits in the length, then lengthen the Baſe in ſo many parts more, and you ſhall alwayes finde the truth hereof. And if you will make a border or Creaſt about this body, then you muſt follow this Rule aforeſaid.</p>
            <p n="41">41 But will you make divers things upon on ground? then it is convenient that firſt you make a pavement, as you ſee it here ſet down, and thereupon frame what you think good upon the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drans, and the leſſe the Quadrans are, and the more in number, you may the eaſier frame things upon them. The croſſe made upon this ground is onely to ſhew you the way and entry thereunto; but for ſuch a forme, you may make a forme of a Chriſtian Church as they are now built. The other forme by it, ſheweth a piece of a founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Houſe, but all theſe things you may make in a greater forme, and ſet them forth as you will; ſometimes placing the Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetall lines in ſuch manner that you may ſee more of the out ſides, but yet the Horiſons muſt ſtand all of one height.</p>
            <p n="42">42 Out of this Superficiall Figure aforeſaid, I have raiſed theſe bodies, to ſhew how the Horiſons of them doe ſtand in the work as well above as below, as you ſhall find by experience, and in truth theſe works which you ſee over the poynts or corners, containe a Book alone by themſelves: but (as I ſaid before) my meaning was to ſhew but three or foure Figures of them, yet I will ſhew ten of them; intending to leave the Student ſome works, whereof I am well aſſured: For that he hath more eyes, and more patience then my ſelfe, he ſhall find many things which I write not of, nor yet ſet down.</p>
            <p n="43">43 Upon this Pavement (as I ſaid) you may forme or frame what you will, but in this Pavement here enſuing, you ſee a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumn lying, being eight ſquare, which is three Quadrants in thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and fourteen in length. This eight ſquare column may be made out of a column of foure-ſquare, as before in another place is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:39210:29"/>ſhewed; which foure-ſquare you may ſee drawn in the Figure with pricks, and the terminations of the eight-ſquare with black lines. But becauſe that this eight-ſquare column is too much ſeen on the ſides, the readier to make it out of the foure-ſquare: I have there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have made an other piece by it, the which, becauſe it draweth nearer to this Horiſon, is ſeen more before, then the other, although not ſo long; for it is but halfe ſo long as the other, as you may ſee and tell it in the ground or foot thereof. And if it were ſo that this eight ſquare Figure reached nearer to the Horiſon, it would then be better ſeen, yet it would not wholly be ſeen before, becauſe it ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth without the four-ſquare and corner.</p>
            <p n="44">44 Theſe Columns are the ſame which are before ſet down, but the other were hollow, and theſe maſſie, whereby an expert work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man may find out many things exerciſing this way, although there are other means to be uſed, as <hi>Albert Durer</hi> hath ſhewed, to look through holes with a thread: There is alſo another way, which is drawn out of flat formes which is the ſureſt way, but very trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and hard to deſcribe in writing; wherefore I have choſen this as the eaſieſt way to be ſhewed. And if I had not undertaken to ſhew other things of more importance, I would have drawn divers bodies and houſes after this manner: But for that I mean to entreat of Scenes, and the preparing of places for to ſhew Comedies and Tragedies, which is now uſed in this age, and eſpecially in <hi>Italy,</hi> therefore I will make an end of theſe foure-cornerd things, leaving it to another (as I ſaid before) to ſet forth more thereof.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Treatiſe of scenes, or places to Play in.</head>
               <figure/>
               <figure/>
               <p n="46">46 Among all the things that may be made by mens hands, thereby to yield admiration, pleaſure to ſight, and to content the fantaſies of men; I think it is placing of a Scene, as it is ſhewed to your ſight, where a man in a ſmall place may ſee built by Carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters or Maſons, ſkilfull in Perſpective work, great Palaces, large Temples, and divers Houſes, both near and far off; broad places filled with Houſes, long ſtreets croſt with other ways: triumphant Arches, high Pillars or Columns, Piramides, Obeliſcens, and a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand faire things and Buildings, adorned with innumerable lights, great, middle ſort, and ſmall, as you may ſee it placed in the Figure, which are ſo cunningly ſet out, that they ſhew forth and repreſent a number of the brighteſt ſtones, as Diamonds, Rubies, Saphirs, Smaragdes, Jacinths, and ſuch like. There you may ſee the bright ſhining Moon aſcending onely with her hornes, and already riſen up, before the Spectators are aware of, or once ſaw it aſcend. In ſome other Scenes you may ſee the riſing of the Sun with his courſe about the world, and at the ending of the Comedy, you may ſee it goe down moſt artificially, whereat many beholders have been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſht. And when occaſion ſerveth, you ſhall by Art fee a God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending down from Heaven; you alſo ſee ſome Comets and Stars ſhoot in the ſkies: then you ſee divers perſonages come upon the Stage, richly adorned with divers ſtrange formes and manners of Apparell both to dance Moriſcoes and play Muſick. Sometimes
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:39210:31"/>you ſee ſtrange Beaſts, wherein are men and children, leaping, run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and Tumbling, as thoſe kind of Beaſts uſe to doe, not without admiration of the beholders: which things, as occaſion ſerveth, are ſo pleaſant to mens eyes, that a man could not ſee fairer made with mens hands. But for that we are entred into another manner of Perſpective work, therefore I will ſpeak more at large thereof. This Perſpective work whereof I will now ſpeak, although it be contrary to thoſe Rules which are ſhewed before, becauſe theſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid are imagined to be upon a flat wall: and this other Rule becauſe it is materiall and imboſſed or raiſed outward, therefore it is reaſon we obſerve another Rule therein, according to common cuſtome. Firſt, you muſt make a Scaffold, which muſt be as high as a mans eye will reach, looking directly forward; for the firſt part thereof which is marked C. But the other part behind it, whereon the Houſes ſtand, you muſt raiſe up behind againſt the wall at leaſt a ninth part thereof, that is, you muſt devide the plaine Stage or Scaffold into nine parts; and then you muſt make the Scaffold higher by a ninth part behind: then before at B, which muſt be very even and ſtrong, becauſe of the Moriſco dancers. This hanging downward of the Scaffold, I have found by experience to be very pleaſing, for in <hi>Vincente</hi> which is as ſumptuous and rich a Town as any in all <hi>Italy,</hi> there I made a Theater and a Stage of wood, then the which, I think, there was never a greater made in our time, in regard of the wonderfull ſights that there were ſeen, as of Wagons, Elephants, and other Moriſcoes. There I ordained, that before the hanging Scene there ſhould be a Scaffold made by water compaſſe, which Scaffold was 12 foot broad, and 60 foot long, according to the place wherein it ſtood, which I found to be very pleaſing and fit for ſhew. This firſt Scaffold, becauſe it was right, therefore the pavement thereof muſt not obey the Horiſon, but the Quadrants, whereof on every ſide were foure-ſquare, from whence at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the riſing Scaffold B, all the Quadrants went to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt Horiſon O, which with their due diſtances doe ſhorten very well. And for that ſome men have placed the Horiſon of this Scio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphies againſt the wall right above the Scaffold, whereby it ſeemeth the Houſes run all in one; therefore I determined to place the Horiſon before the door, which pleaſed me ſo well, that I uſed the ſame kind of order in all theſe kind of works: and ſo I counſell thoſe that take pleaſure in ſuch Arts, to uſe and eſteem this way for the beſt, as I will ſhew in this Figure following, and have alſo decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the profill of the Theater and Scene.</p>
               <p>And becauſe the preparation for Comedies are done in three ſorts, that is, Comicall, Tragicall, and Satiricall; I will firſt entreat of the Comicall, whereof the Houſes muſt be made as if they were for common or ordinary people, which for the moſt part muſt be made under roofs in a Halls, which at the end thereof hath a chamber for the pleaſure or eaſe of the Perſonages; and there it is that the ground of the Scaffold is made (as I ſaid and ſhewed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) in the Profill. Therefore C is the firſt part being the flat Scaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold; and ſuppoſe that each Quadran containeth two foot on either
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:39210:31"/>ſide, ſo ſhall they upon the hanging Scaffold before on the Baſe be alſo two foot broad, which is marked B. And (as I ſaid before) my meaning is not to place the Horiſon hereof againſt the back behind in the Scaffold, but as far as it is from the beginning of the pave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment B to the wall, ſo far I would alſo that men ſhall paſſe behinde through the wall, and ſo ſhall all the houſes and other things ſhew better in the ſhortning: and when by convenient diſtances you have drawn all the Quadrants towards the Horiſon, and ſhortned them, then you muſt ſhorten the Houſes right with the four-ſquare ſtones, which houſes are the great lines marked upon the ground, as well for thoſe that ſtand upright as thoſe that ſhorten. All ſuch houſes I alwayes made of ſpars, or rafters, or laths, covered with linnen cloth; making doors and windowes, both before and in the ſhortning, as occaſion fell out. I have alſo made ſomethings of halfe planks of wood, which were great help to the Painters to ſet out things at life. All the ſpaces from the back to the wall marked A ſhall be for the Perſonages, to the which end the hindermoſt back in the middle ſhall ſtand at the leaſt two foot from the wall, that the Perſonages may goe from the one ſide to the other, and not be ſeen. Then you muſt raiſe a termination at the beginning of the pavement B, which ſhall be the poynt L, and from thence to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon there ſhall be a line drawn, as it is marked in the profill with pricks, which ſhall be of like height, and where that toucheth the hindermoſt back of the Scene or Scaffold, there the Horiſon of that back ſhall ſtand, and that Horiſon ſhall ſerve onely for that back. But if you ſtretch a cord or any other thing to the termination L, then you may faſten a thred to it, to thruſt backward or forward to uſe it out of the ſtedfaſt Horiſon, and all the Ortography of the houſes before. But the Horiſon which goeth through the wall ſhall ſerve for all the ſhortning ſides of the houſes; and for that men ſhould break the wall, if they would uſe all this Horiſon in groſſe, which may not be done, therefore I have alwayes made a ſmall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell of wood and Paper juſt of the ſame bigneſſe, and by the ſame modell ſet it down in groſſe, from piece to piece. But this way will fall out hard for ſome men to underſtand, nevertheleſſe, it will be neceſſary to work by modells and experiments, and by ſtudy a man ſhall finde the way: and for that a man can hardly find any Halls how great ſoever, wherein he can place a Theater without imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and impediment; therefore to follow Antiquities, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my power and ability, I have made all ſuch parts of theſe Theaters, as may ſtand in a hall. Therefore the part marked D ſhall be the poſt ſcene, and the circular place marked E ſhall be the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſtra: round about this Orcheſtra ſhall be the places for the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſt perſonages to ſit, marked F. The firſt ſteps marked G for the nobleſt women to ſit upon. The place H is a way, ſo is the part marked I. In the middle between theſe degrees are ſteps the eaſier to goe up.</p>
               <p>The places marked K muſt be made ſo great backward as the Hall will afford, which is made ſomewhat flooping, that the people may ſee one over the others head.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:39210:32"/>
               <p n="47">47 Touching the diſpoſition of Theaters and other Scenes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the grounds thereof, I have ſpoken ſufficiently; now I will ſpeak of the Scene in Perſpective work: and for that Scenes are made of three ſorts, that is, Comicall to play Comedies on, Tragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call for Tragedies, and Satiricall for Satirs. This firſt ſhall be Comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, whereas the houſes muſt be ſlight for Citizens, but eſpecially there muſt not want a brawthell or bawdy houſe, and a great Inne, and a Church; ſuch things are of neceſſity to be therein. How to raiſe theſe houſes from the ground is ſufficiently expreſſed, and how you ſhall place the Horiſon: nevertheleſſe, that you may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be inſtructed (touching the former of theſe Houſes) I have here ſet down a Figure, for ſatisfaction of thoſe that take pleaſure there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; but becauſe this Figure is ſo ſmall, therein I could not obſerve all the meaſures, but refer them to invention, that thereby you may chuſe or make houſes which ſhew well, as an open Gallery, or lodge, through the which you may ſee another houſe. The hangings over or ſhooting out, ſhew well in ſhortning work, and ſome Cornices cut out at the ends; accompanied with ſome others that are pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſhew well in work: ſo doe the houſes which have great bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring out, like lodgings or Chambers for men, and eſpecially above all things, you muſt ſet the ſmalleſt houſes before, that you may ſee other houſes over or above them, as you ſee it here above the baw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy houſe; for if you place the greateſt before, and the reſt behind ſtill leſſen, then the place of the Scene would not be ſo well filled, and although theſe things upon the one ſide be made all upon one floor; nevertheleſſe, for that you place great part of the lights in the middle, hanging over the Scene or Scaffold, therefore it would frand better if the floor in the midſt were taken away, and all the roundells and quadrans which you ſee in the Buildings, they are artificiall lights cutting through, of divers colours, which to make I will ſhew the manner in the laſt of this Book. The windows which ſtand before, were good to be made of Glaſſe or Paper, with light behind them. But if I ſhould here write all that I know to ſerve for this work, it would be overlong to reherſe; therefore I refer that to the wit and diſcretion of thoſe that exerciſe and practiſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves herein.</p>
               <p n="48">48 Houſes for Tragedies, muſt be made for great perſonages, for that actions of love, ſtrange adventures, and cruell murthers, (as you read in ancient and modern Tragedies) happen alwayes in the houſes of great Lords, Dukes, Princes, and Kings. Therefore in ſuch caſes you muſt make none but ſtately houſes, as you ſee it here in this Figure, wherein (for that it is ſo ſmall) I could make no Princely Pallaces, but it is ſufficient for the workman to ſee the manner thereof, whereby he may help himſelf as time and place ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth: and (as I ſaid in the Comical) he muſt always ſtudy to pleaſe the eyes of the beholders, and forget not himſelfe ſo much as to ſet a ſmall building in ſtead of a great, for the reaſons aforeſaid. And for that I have made all my Scenes of laths, covered over with linnen, yet ſometime it is neceſſary to make ſome things riſing or boſſing out, which are to be made of wood, like the houſes on the left ſide,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:39210:32"/>whereof the Pillars, although they ſhorten, ſtand all upon one Baſe with ſome ſtayres, all covered over with cloth, the Cornices bearing out, which you muſt obſerve to the middle part: But to give place to the Galleries, you muſt ſet the other ſhortning Cloth ſomewhat backwards, and make a Cornice above it, as you ſee: and that which I ſpeak of theſe Buildings, you muſt underſtand of all the the reſt, but in the Buildings which ſtand far backward, the Painting work muſt ſupply the place by ſhadows without any bearing out: touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the artificiall lights, I have ſpoken thereof in the Comicall works. All that you make above the Roofe ſticking out, as Chim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys, Towers, Piramides, Obliſces, and other ſuch like things or Images, you muſt make them all of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n boards, cut out round, and well coloured: But if you make any flat Buildings, they muſt ſtand ſomewhat far inward, that you may not ſee them on the ſides. In theſe Scenes, although ſome have painted perſonages therein like ſupporters, as in a Gallery, or do r, as a Dog, Cat, or any other Beaſts; I am not of that opinion, for that ſtandeth too long without ſtirring or moving; but if you make ſuch a thing to lie ſleeping, that I hold withall. You may alſo make Images, Hiſtories, or Fables of Marble, or other matter againſt a wall; but to repreſent the life, they ought to ſtir. In the latter end of this Book I will ſhew you how to make them.</p>
               <p n="49">49 The Satiricall Scenes are to repreſent Satirs, wherein you muſt place all thoſe things that be rude and ruſticall, as in ancient Satirs they were made plaine without any reſpect, whereby men might underſtand, that ſuch things were referred to Ruſticall peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which ſet all things out rudely and plainly: for which cauſe <hi>Vitruvius,</hi> ſpeaking of Scenes, ſaith, they ſhould be made with Trees, Roots, Herbs, Hills, and Flowres, and with ſome country houſes, as you ſee them here ſet down. And for that in our dayes theſe things were made in Winter, when there were but few green Trees, Herbs, and Flowres to be found; then you muſt make theſe things of Silk, which will be more commendable then the naturall things themſelves: and as in other Scenes for Comedies or Tragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, the houſes or other artificiall things are Painted, ſo you muſt make Trees, Hearbs, and other things in theſe; and the more ſuch things coſt, the more they are eſteemed, for they are things which ſtately and great Perſons doe, which are enemies to nigardlineſſe This have I ſeen in ſome Scenes made by <hi>Jeronimo Genga,</hi> for the pleaſure and delight of his Lord and Patron <hi>Eranciſco Maria,</hi> Duke of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbin;</hi> wherein I ſaw ſo great liberality uſed by the Prince and ſo good a conceit in the workman, and ſo good Art and proportion in things therein preſented, as ever I ſaw in all my life before. On good Lord, what magnificence was there to be ſeen, for the great number of Trees and Fruits, with ſundry Hearbs and Flowres, all made of fine Silk of divers colours. The water-courſes being ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with Frogs, Snayles, Tortuſes, Toads, Adders, Snakes, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beaſts: Roots of Corrale, mother of Pearle, and other ſhells laid and thruſt through between the ſtones, with ſo many ſeverall and faire things, that if I ſhould declare them all, I ſhould not have
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:39210:33"/>time enough. I ſpeak not of Satirs, Nimphs, Mer-maids, divers Monſters, and other ſtrange beaſts, made ſo cunningly, that they ſeemed in ſhew as if they went and ſtirred, according to their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. And if I were not deſirous to be briefe, I would ſpeak of the coſtly apparell of ſome Shepheards made of cloth of Gold, and of Silk, cunningly mingled with Imbrothery; I would alſo ſpeak of ſome Fiſhermen, which were no leſſe richly apparalled then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, having Nets and Angling-rods, all guilt: I ſhould ſpeak of ſome Country maids and Nimphs careleſly apparelled without pride, but I leave all theſe things to the diſcretion and conſideration of the judicious workman, which ſhall make all ſuch things as their Pattrons ſerve them, which they muſt work after their own devices, and never take care what it ſhall coſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Artificiall Lights of the Scenes.</head>
               <p>I Promiſed in the Treatiſe of Scenes to ſet down the manner how to make theſe lights ſhining through, of divers colours, and firſt I will ſpeak of a ſure colour which is like a to Zaphir, and yet ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what fairer. Take a piece of Salamoniack, and put it into a Barbers Baſen, or ſuch like thing, and put water into it: then bruiſe it ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly therein, till it be all molten, alwayes putting more water unto it, as you deſire to have it light or ſad colour; which done, if you will have it faier and clear, then ſtraine it through a fine cloth into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther veſſell, and then it will be a clear Celeſtiall blew, whereof you may make divers kinds of blew with water. Will you make an Emerauld colour? then put ſome Saffron as you will have it pale or high coloured; for here it is not neceſſary to preſcribe you any weight or meaſure, for that experience will teach you how to doe it. If you will make a Rubby colour, if you be in a place where you may have red Wine, then you need not uſe any other thing, but to make it pall with water, as need requireth: but if you can get no Wine, then take Braſill beaten to powder, and put it into a Kettell of water with Allum, let it ſeeth, and ſcum it well; then ſtraine it and uſe it with Water and Vineger. If you will counterfeit a Ballays, you muſt make it of red and white Wine mingled together; but white Wine alone will ſhew like a Topaz or a Criſolite: The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duit or common water being ſtrained, will be like a Diamond, and to doe this well, you muſt upon a glaſſie ground frame certaine points or tablets, and fill them with water. The manner to ſet theſe ſhining colours in their places, is thus, Behind the painted houſe wherein theſe painted colours ſhall ſtand, you muſt ſet a thin board cut out in the ſame manner that theſe lights ſhall be placed, whether it be round or ſquare, cornered of ovale, like an Egge; and behinde the ſame board there ſhall be another ſtronger board laid flat behind them, for the bottles and other manner of glaſſes with theſe waters to ſtand in, muſt be placed againſt the holes, as it ſhall neceſſarily fall out, but they muſt be ſet faſt, leſt they fall with leaping and dancing of the Moriſcoes. And behind the glaſſes you muſt ſet great Lamps, that the light may alſo be ſtedfaſt; and if the bottels
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:39210:33"/>or other veſſells of glaſſe on the ſide where the light ſtands were flat; or rather hollow, it would rather ſhew the clearer, and the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours moſt excellent and faire; the like muſt be done with the holes on the ſhortning ſide: But if you need a great light to ſhew more then the reſt, then ſet a torch behind, and behind the torch a bright Baſon, the brightneſſe wereof will ſhew like the beams of the Sun. You may alſo make glaſſe of all colours and formes, ſome foure-ſquare, ſome with croſſes, and any other forme with their light be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them. Now all the lights ſerving for the colours, ſhall not be the ſame which muſt light the Scene, for you muſt have a great number of torches before the Scene. You may alſo place certaine candleſticks above the Scene with great Candles therein, and above the Candleſticks you may place ſome veſſells with water, wherein you may put a piece of Camphir, which burning will ſhew a very good light, and ſmell well. Sometime it may chance that you muſt make ſomething or other which ſhould ſeem to burn, which you muſt wet throughly with excellent good Aquavite; and ſetting it it on fire with a Candle it will burn all over; and although I could ſpeak more of theſe fires, yet this ſhall ſuffice for this time; and I will ſpeak of ſome things that are pleaſing to the beholders.</p>
               <p>The while that the Scene is empty of perſonages, then the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man muſt have certaine Figures or formes ready of ſuch greatneſſe as the place where they muſt ſtand will afford them to be, which muſt be made of paſt-board, cut out round and painted, ſignifying ſuch things as you will, which Figures muſt leane againſt a rule or lath of wood, croſſe over the Scene where any gate, door, or way is made, and there ſome one or other behind the door muſt make the Figures paſſe along, ſometime in forme of Muſitians with Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſome like ſingers; and behind the Scene ſome muſt play on, upon certaine Inſtruments, and ſing alſo. Sometime you muſt make a number of footmen and horſemen, going about with Trumpets, Pifes and Drums, at which time you muſt play with Drums, Trumpets and Pifes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> very ſoftly behind, which will keep the peoples eyes occupied, and content them well.</p>
               <p>If it be requiſite to make a Planet, or any other thing, to paſſe along in the Aire, it muſt be framed and cut out of paſt-board; then in the hindermoſt and back part of the houſes of the Scene, there muſt be a piece of wire drawn above in the roofe of the houſe and made faſt with certaine rings behind to the paſt-board painted with a Planet, or any other thing, that ſhall be drawn ſoftly by a man with a black thred from one end to the other, but it muſt be far from mens ſight, that neither of the threds may be ſeen.</p>
               <p>Sometime you have occaſion to ſhew thunder and lightning, as the play requireth: then you muſt make thunder in this manner, Commonly all Scenes are made at the end of a great Hail, whereas uſually there is a Chamber above it, wherein you muſt roule a great Bullet of a Cannon, or of ſome other great Ordnance, and then counterfeit Thunder. Lightning muſt be made in this manner, there muſt be a man placed behind the Scene or Scaffold, in a high place, with a box in his hand, the cover whereof muſt be full with
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:39210:34"/>holes, and in the middle of that place there ſhall be a burning Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle placed, the box muſt be filled with powder of vernis or ſulphire, and caſting his hand with the box upwards the powder flying in the Candle, will ſhew as if it were Lightning. But touching the beams of the Lightning, you muſt draw a piece of wire over the Scene, which muſt hang downwards, whereon you muſt put a ſquib cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red over with pure gold, or ſhining lattin, which you will; and while the Bullet is rouling, you muſt ſhoot of ſome piece of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and with the ſame giving fire to the ſquibs, it will work the effect which is deſired.</p>
               <p>It would be overlong if I ſhould ſpeak of all things which are to be uſed in theſe affaires, therefore I will leave ſpeaking of Perſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive things.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:39210:34"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
